A Guide to the Alexandra Ripley Papers 1966-1967, 1985-1992
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Alexandra Ripley Papers 1966-1967, 1985-1992
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10624-h
This collection consists of 825 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The permission of Alexandra Ripley is required for access to the collection, copying, and all quotations.
Acquisition Information
This collection was loaned to the Library by Alexandra Ripley, Keswick, Virginia, on December 1, 1992.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of novelist Alexandra Ripley of Keswick, Virginia, consists of ca. 825 items (17 Hollinger boxes, ca. 7 linear feet), 1966-1967 and 1985-1992, chiefly pertaining to the writing and publishing of Scarlett by Ripley, including autograph manuscripts, typescripts, correspondence with her agency, publishers, and editors, fan mail, newspaper clippings, postcards, photographs, memorabilia, audiotapes, computer disks, a videotape recording, and research material about the historical background of the novel, including folders on Atlanta, Ireland, Charleston, and Savannah
Arrangement
Manuscripts of the book Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley comprise the first series. Also included is a Dove Audio typescript of Charleston, a talk to booksellers in Atlanta by Ripley, and various writing assignments and notes for a night class with Richard Coleman in Charleston, South Carolina by Alexandra Ripley.
The second series consists of miscellaneous and research files, including fan mail; correspondence with her agents, publisher, and friends; the American Booksellers Association Convention in New York City; the promotional tour for Editions Belfond, France; Gone With the Wind Forum, Richmond, Virginia; the Life excerpt from Scarlett, with autograph corrections and changes (1991 Jun); Life photographs of Alexandra Ripley by Lynn Johnson [1988]; newsclippings and articles about Scarlett; publicity and press releases; photographs and postcards; cassette recordings; promotional material for Scarlett; and research material, including books used in research and copies of Scarlett and Gone With The Wind.
The correspondence file contains a draft of Ripley's letter to the Atlanta representatives of the Mitchell estate concerning the story line for Scarlett. The letter defends her choice of Ireland in the novel as an outlet for the explosive nature of Scarlett as presented by Mitchell in Gone With The Wind. Ripley contends that Margaret Mitchell effectively closed the familiar scenes of Atlanta, Tara, and Charleston to Scarlett. Ireland provides a largely unknown historical setting that has a rich mythology but which is also violent and stormy enough to furnish a suitable backdrop for the character of Scarlett (1987 Oct 9); a draft of a letter from Ripley to her lawyer in New York, Bob Youdelman, about her difficulties with her agent William Morris, and asking for advice (1988 Feb 27); and two notes from Barbara Mertz about the success of Scarlett and the progress of her next Amelia book (ca. 1992 Jan 1) and auction plans (Fall 1992).
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - 2 AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Very Early Versions of the Sequel to Gone With the Wind in Brief Summaries [ca. 1987] (Box 1)
  - Ams Preparatory Study of Margaret Mitchell's Writing Technique used in Gone With the Wind[ca. 1987] (Box 1)
  - 2 Ams Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outline of the Novel, with a companion Outline of Gone With the Wind[ca. 1987 Sep] (Box 1)
  - Ams & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outline of the Novel, 68 pages, with autograph changes and corrections 1987 Sep 21 (Box 1)
  - Tms Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outline of the Novel, 78 pages, with a companion outline of Gone With the Wind, with a draft of Ripley's letter to Robert [Gottlieb ?] 1987 Sep 21 (Box 1)
  - 3 Tms Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outline of the Novel, 78 pages (2 folders) 1987 Sep 21 (Box 1)
  - 2 Tms Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outline of the Novel, 78 pages, with a companion outline of Gone With the Wind 1987 Sep 21 (Box 1)
  - Ams & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 1 & 2, with autograph corrections & changes in red ink, 41 pages [1988 Jan 26] (Box 1)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 1 & 2, First Draft, pages 6-62, with autograph changes & corrections [1988 Feb 2] (Box 1)
  - AMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 1 & 2, First Draft, pages 1-62 (Revised), with autograph changes & corrections in red [1988 Feb 2] (Box 1)
  - 3 TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 1 & 2, 39 pages, with a letter to Robert Gottlieb, William Morris Agency, February 11, 1988, about the projected novel 1988 Feb 11 (Box 2)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 1 & 2, with autograph corrections in red ink, 46 pages [1988?] (Box 2)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Part I, with autograph revisions in red and black ink, 42 pages [1989?] (Box 2)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book I, beginning with Chapter 3, pages 1-57 1989 May (Box 2)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books II-IV A, Chapters 7-78 (5 folders) 1989 May-Jul (Box 2)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book IV B, Chapters 79-104 [1989?] (Box 3)
  - AMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Protection Copy(5 folders) 1989 (Box 3)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, First Edit, pages 1-928 (6 folders) [1989] (Box 4)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, First Edit, pages 929-1058 [1989] (Box 5)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Part I, after first edit, with revision by Ripley, pages 1-112 1989 June (Box 5)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books I-II, First Rewrite 433 pages (4 folders) [1989?] (Box 5)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book III, [Second Draft ?], pages 373-518, with autograph corrections by the author [1989?] (Box 5)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book IV, [Second Draft ?], pages 508-832, with autograph corrections by the author (2 folders) [1989?] (Box 6)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Miscellaneous Loose Pages [1989?] (Box 6)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, pages 90-745, (4 folders) 1990 Mar 15 (Box 6)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, pages 746-979 1990 Mar 15 (Box 7)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, First Draft, Pages cut prior to submission 1990 Mar 15 (Box 7)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Comments & Critique of the Novel by the editor Jeanne Bernkopf 1990 Apr-Nov (Box 7)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books I-III, first revisions by the editor Jeanne Bernkopf (5 folders) [1990 Apr?] (Box 7)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 44-54, first revisions by the editor Jeanne Bernkopf (2 folders) [1990 Apr ?] (Box 8)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books I-II, second revision with autograph corrections by the author (3 folders) [1990 Jul ?] (Box 8)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books I-II, after the second revision by the editor (3 folders) 1990 Aug 30 (Box 8)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book IV, Final Rewrite, pages 508-932 (3 folders) [1990 Oct ?] (Box 9)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book IV Second Revision (Final), with autograph corrections by the author, pages 833-899 1990 Nov (Box 9)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books I-II, Final Typescript (3 folders) 1990 Dec (Box 9)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books III-IV, Final Typescript (4 folders) 1990 Dec (Box 10)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Book I-II (3 folders) [1990 Dec] (Box 10)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Books III-IV (4 folders) [1990 Dec] (Box 11)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Miscellaneous Pages with autograph changes & corrections [1990 Dec] (Box 11)
  - AMs & TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Final Round of Revisions, with the report on the novel by Warner Books, Inc. and revisions by Jeanne Bernkopf 1991 Jan (Box 11)
  - TMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Bernkopf Edit and Partial Copy, editing accepted by Warner Books, Inc. at final meeting 1991 Jan (Box 11)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Final Revisions, with a list of revisions to be made and corrected pages 45-73 1991 Apr 21 (Box 11)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Outtakes, Miscellaneous Pages n.d. (Box 11)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Miscellaneous Notes re Writing In Progressn.d. (Box 12)
  - AMs Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Miscellaneous Notes (2 folders) n.d. (Box 12)
  - TMs Dove Audio Presents Charleston by Alexandra Ripley, typescript with autograph changes and corrections by the author 1992 Apr-Jun (Box 12)
  - AMs Talk to Booksellers in Atlanta, Georgia, by Alexandra Ripley about writing Scarlett, 8 pages 1991 Sep [22 ?] (Box 12)
  - AMs & TMs Writing Assignments & Notes for a night class with Richard Coleman, Charleston, South Carolina, by Alexandra Ripley 1966-1967 (Box 12)
  - AMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, pages 1-50, 80-211, 284-600 (7 folders 1990 Jan & n.d. (Box 18)
  - AMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, pages 601-1185 (4 folders) n.d. (Box 19)
  - AMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Chapters 76-78, incomplete n.d. (Box 19)
  - TMs (EC) Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Miscellaneous Pages n.d. (Box 19)
  - Financial Papers re Graley Inc., Lafayette Hill Tavern, Keswick, Virginia 1989 (Box 19)
- Series II: Miscellaneous & Research Series
  - American Booksellers Association Convention, New York 1991 May (Box 12)
  - Correspondence with Agents, Publisher, and Friends, including two notes from Barbara Mertz 1987-1992 (Box 12)
  - Editions Belfond Promotional Tour for Scarlett, including photographs of Alexandra Ripley, Biarritz, France (2 folders) 1992 Jan (Box 12)
  - Fan Mail re Scarlett(7 folders) 1991-1992 (Box 13)
  - Gone With The Wind Forum, Richmond, Virginia 1991 Nov 9-10 (Box 13)
  - Page Proof Life Excerpt from Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, with autograph corrections and changes, 41 pages 1991 Jun (Box 14)
  - Life Photographs of Alexandra Ripley by Lynn Johnson [1988] (Box 14)
  - Newclippings & Articles re Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley 1988, 1991-1992 (Box 14)
  - Photographs & Postcards - Miscellaneous ca. 1985-1992 (Box 14)
  - Publicity & Press Releases re Scarlett 1991-1992 (Box 14)
  - Research Material 1988 & n.d. (Box 14)
  - Research Material - Atlanta 1987 (Box 14)
  - Research Material - Charleston 1987-1988 (Box 14)
  - (EC) Research Material - Charleston - Copies of Middleton Family Letters (2 folders) [1871] (Box 14)
  - (EC) Research Material - Charleston - Copies of Middleton Family Letters (3 folders) [1872-73, 1875] (Box 15)
  - Research Material - Ireland (2 folders) ca. 1987-1988, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Research Material - Miami, Florida (Vizcaya) n.d. (Box 15)
  - Research Material - Savannah n.d. (Box 15)
  - Research Notebooks [1987-1988 ?] (Box 15)
  - Research Trip to Ireland - Expenses 1987 (Box 15)
  - Memorabilia re Scarlett and Gone With The Wind1991 & n.d. (Box 16)
  - Books Used for Research for Scarlett(4 volumes) ca. 1987-1990 (Box 16)
  - Life articles re Alexandra Ripley and the excerpt from Scarlett1988 & 1991 (Box 16)
  - 13 disks Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Drafts of the Novel and Miscellaneous Computer Disks labelled JOE A-Y& JOE MISC1990 (Box 16)
  - Printed Charleston and On Leaving Charleston by Alexandra Ripley, Warner Books 1991 (Box 17)
  - Printed Gone With The Wind by Margaret Mitchell, 50th Anniversary First Edition Facsimile, The Macmillan Company 1986 (Box 17)
  - Printed Lost Country Life by Dorothy Hartley, Pantheon Books 1979 (Box 17)
  - Printed Scarlett by Alexandra Ripley, Warner Books 1991 (Box 17)
  - Printed Scarlett's Women by Helen Taylor, Rutgers University Press 1989 (Box 17)
  - Printed A Song For Ireland by Mary O'Hara, Michael Joseph Limited 1982 (Box 17)
  - Cardboard Promotional Display Figure of Scarlett(unfoldered) and a cardboard display of Scarlett with printed slips to reserve personal copies of the book from Warner Books, with a poster advertising Scarlett (3 items) 1991 (Oversize 7)
- Cassette Tape Recordings
  - Patrick Ball Celtic Harp - The Music of Turlough O'Carolan and From A Distant Time(2 tapes) 1982-1983, casette tape recording
  - Irish Language Tape 1986, casette tape
  - Phone Conversations of Alexandra Ripley with friends, her editor, and agent concerning the writing and publication of Scarlett(19 tapes) ca. 1988-1991
  - Radio Interview with Alexandra Ripley by Milt Rosenberg, Chicago WGN Radio concerning Scarlett1991 Oct 2
- Videotape Recording
  - Scarlett/Alexandra Ripley Local New York, Network, Washington Coverage (Schedule Enclosed) 1991 Sep 25-27